字幕翻译制作：goodliuwu
（庆祝博伊德彗星 莫扎特）
不不，不不，首先你应该找到…
No, no. No, no. First, you should find out
宇宙的本质属性是什么
what is the essential nature of the universe.
宇宙是一个固有非理性的地方…
Is the universe an inherently irrational place
随机而又混乱吗？
random and chaotic?
对，但是你…
Ya, but you...
花栗鼠，你的勺子
Chipmunk, your spoon.
你的勺子…掉地上了
Your spoon--it's on the floor.
你们准备点餐了吗？
Are you ready to order?
呃，是的，我想是的
Uh, yes, I think.
照惯例，有劳
The usual, please.
不，我要来一杯咖啡
No. I'll have a cup of coffee
还有一个玉米松饼，有劳
and a corn muffin, please.
亲，你的惯例就是这些
Darling, that is your usual.
哦，那我就要那些吧
Well, I'll have that then.
- 好的  - 谢谢
- Okay. - Thank you.
- 啊哈  - 怎么？
- Aha! - What?
它每平方厘米流失11000个分子
It loses 11,000 molecules per square centimeter
每秒
per second.
什么东西？
What does?
那颗彗星
The comet.
来
Now...
这些你最喜欢哪个？
which one of these do you like best?
这是性格测试吗？
Is this a personality test?
呣，算是个惊喜吧
Mm, it's a sort of surprise.
它们都一样
They're all the same.
什么？不不，看
What? No, no. Look.
那是碧绿色
That's aquamarine.
那是蓝绿，那个是藻绿
That's blue-green, and that's algae.
哦，你知道在原子层面上没有颜色这种东西
Well, you know at the atomic level there's no such thing as color.
不过，他们那次的确在比利时做过那个研究
Though they did do that study in Belgium that time--
等等
Wait.
还是在丹麦？
or was it Denmark?
- 唠叨  - 总之...
- Babbling. - Anyway.
唠叨
Babbling.
总之，重点在于…
Anyway, the point was that...
重点在于什么？
What was the point?
哦，既然质子远小于光波
Oh, that since protons are so much smaller than light waves...
藻绿
Algae.
谢谢
Thank you.
既然质子远小于光波
Since protons are so much smaller than light waves
他们怎么能看到它来起头呢？
how could they ever see it to begin with?
哦，那些丹麦人
Oh, those Danes.
还是说在所有事物的背后都有一个基本的秩序？
Or is there a fundamental order underlying all things?
（坠落的星尘里有现金）
喂，惊奇队长？
Hey, Captain Marvel?
沙赞？
Shazam?
哦，谢谢
Oh, thanks.
我刚才在读博伊德彗星的报道
I was just reading about Boyd's comet.
博伊德什么？
Boyd's what?
彗星？天上的？
Comet? Like in the sky?
他们说它很快要到这里来了
They say it's going to be here soon.
我们有可能看到它
We're going to be able to see it.
你们知道为什么彗星的尾巴总是远离太阳那面吗？
You know why a comet's tail always points away from the sun?
不知道
No.
想知道吗？
Want to know?
- 不  - 不
- No. - No.
因为它其实根本不是一条尾巴，它是…
'Cause it's actually not a tail at all. It's...
它是太阳照亮的气体颗粒群
It's bits of gas that the sun lights up.
我们地球人会尽量记住这一点
We earthlings will try to keep that in mind.
就像一个500英里长的泽西喷灯
Kind of like a 500-mile-long Jersey torch.
哇
Wow.
那一定是真的
It must be true.
该事实仍然说明某些事件是完全偶发的
The fact remains that certain events are strictly accidental.
什么事实？
What fact?
哦，天啊
Oh, my,
看看时间
look at the time.
没问题
No problem.
是因为春天的关系
It's because it's spring.
每一样东西在春天里都会经历剧变，你说呢？
Everything goes through upheaval in the spring, wouldn't you say?
别这样，小贱人
Come on, you little bitch.
听着像是来生意了
Sounds like business.
名爵TF跑车
M.G.T.F. Roadster.
奥斯汀希利
Austin-Healey.
凯迪拉克Coupe
Cadillac coupe.
- 一块  - 跟你赌了
- Buck. - You're on.
进气阀爆裂
Blown intake valve.
不，分电盘盖破裂
No. Cracked distributor cap.
消声器报废
Busted muffler.
我们都是某一滑稽的宇宙事故的受害者
Are we all victims of some comic cosmic accident
还是说有一个大设计？
or is there a grand design?
哦，真走运
Oh, what luck.
- TC跑车  - 是一辆TF
- T.C. Roadster. - That's a T.F.
一对大学上等人
A couple of college swells.
你应付他们，艾德
You handle them, Ed.
嗨，哪里有问题了？
Hi, what seems to be the problem?
你们这里有人懂怎么修理英国车的吗？
Do you have anyone here who knows how to deal with British automobiles?
我真的不希望有人拿根尖棍子在里面乱戳
I really don't want anyone just poking around in there with a sharp stick.
我看看引擎盖下面没问题吧？
Would it be all right if I looked under the bonnet?
哦，至少他称之为引擎盖
Well, at least he called it a bonnet.
所以，这就是引擎了，是吧？
so, that's the engine, huh?
你看，我想也许我们应该去别的地方，你说呢？
Um, look, I think, perhaps we ought to go somewhere else, do you?
进气阀，我告诉你
Intake valve, I'm tellin' ya.
消声器报废
Busted muffler.
- 进气阀  - 消声器
- Intake valve. - Busted muffler.
那就是你的问题
That's your problem right there.
什么？
What?
你没有火花 热情
You got no spark.
什么？
What?
你没有火花
You have no spark.
对，我听见他说的了，凯瑟琳
Yes, I heard him, Catherine.
你觉得这话是什么意思？
What do you think it means?
是发电机的问题吗？
Is it the generator?
是线圈？是什么？
The coil? What?
哦，这个难说
Well, it's hard to say.
你看，你有一台卢卡斯四型发电机
You see, you have a Lucas type four generator
是12伏特系统，可你知道英国人的
on a 12-volt system, and you know the British.
他们宁愿花时间在仪表盘上粘木头
They'd rather spend time gluing wood on a dashboard
也不愿把电力系统搞好
than getting the electrical system right.
绝妙，可是…
Fascinating, but...
可是这车出了什么毛病？
but what is wrong with the car?
哦，我猜想是你的行程太短
Well, my guess is your stroke is too short
而且你还过早地点火
and you're getting premature ignition.
是不是有过这样的感觉？
Does it ever feel that way?
说什么呢？
Like what?
说行程太短了，而且…
Like the stroke is too short and...
还点火过早了？
you're getting premature ignition?
哦，我肯定我不知道你什么意思
Well, I'm sure I don't know what you mean.
你能不能至少暂时把它修好，你觉得呢？
Could you just fix it at least temporarily, do you think?
我说，我们真的落后进度了
I mean, we're really running behind schedule here.
我跟我老板确认一下
I'll check with my boss.
不要走开
Don't go away.
他似乎人挺好
He seems nice enough.
他，他是个穴居人
He's, he's a troglodyte.
进气阀，对吧？
Intake valve, right?
消声器报废？
Busted muffler?
我要娶她
I'm going to marry her.
- 谁？那个贵妇？  - 对
- Who? The dame? - Yeah.
哇，够快的
Wow, that was fast.
车怎么样？
What about the car?
分电盘盖破裂
Cracked distributor cap.
你不会相信的，我看着她，她看着我，然后
You wouldn't believe it. I looked at her, she looked at me, and...
就…就发生了，你可以感觉得到
it was... it happened. You could feel it.
就像是死去，只是以一种好的方式
It was like death, but in a good way.
他发癫了
He's going screwy.
啪 啪 啪 啪
Pop, pop, pop, pop.
那是电
It was electric.
然后，然后我亲吻了她
And then, then I kissed her.
你亲了一个顾客？什么时候？
You kissed a customer? When?
在未来
In the future.
好奇怪，就好像时间和空间全都…
It was weird. It was like time and space got all...
…混在一起
mixed up and...
就像是火星人思想融合
it was like a Martian mind-meld.
- 他要崩溃了  - 好了，听着
- He's cracking up. - All right, look,
我要你远离那些杂志
I want you to stay away from the magazines.
- 这是命令  - 不不，你不明白
- That's an order. - No, no. You don't understand.
就是，就是，对了…
It was, it was, okay...
过去，现在，还有未来
the past, the present, and the future
全都来到一起
they all went together.
我跟她有了孩子，我能看见孩子们
I had kids with her. I could see the kids.
- 我有过两个男孩和三个…  - 对  - 不
- I had two boys and three... - Yes. - No.
三个男孩，两个男孩…
Three boys, two boys...
打扰了
WOMAN: Excuse me?
这些一共要花多久？
How long will all this take?
哦，这取决于你
Well, that's up to you.
是吗？
It is?
车啊，你个呆头
The car, you nut.
呃，我，哦…
Um, I, uh...
车，过几天
the car, a few days.
那么久？
That long?
我必须对它全身心投入
I'm going to have to give it my full attention.
哦，那样的话我最好是打个电话
Well, in that case, I better call a phone.
你介意我用你们的电话箱吗？
Do you mind if I use your cab?
办公室里有一部电话箱
There's a cab in the office.
对 [德语]，但是测不准原理假设了一个混乱的宇宙
Ja, but the uncertainty principle postulates a universe of chaos
一切的发生仅仅是偶然
where everything happens merely by chance.
（未来 科幻小说）
谢谢你
thank you.
怎么啦？
What's going on?
我们来处理
We're gonna take care of it.
哈罗？我需要一辆出租车
Hello? I need a taxi.
呃，凯瑟琳·博伊德
Uh, Catherine Boyd.
博伊德
B-O-Y-D.
什么？哦
What? Oh.
这里的地址是什么？
What's the address here?
- 布罗德130号  - 布罗德130号
- 130 Broad. - 130 Broad.
先停在塞拉斯·潘恩研究所
The first stop is the Silas Paine Institute
然后我要去默瑟112号
then I'm going on to 112 Mercer.
（通俗科学月刊）
那是你的地址吗？
Is that your address?
默瑟112号
112 Mercer.
两分钟！谢谢
Two minutes! Thank you.
拜
Bye.
哦，哈
Oh, huh!
- 那个…  - 啥
- Well...  - Yeah.
那是比利时
it was Belgium.
是吗？是什么？
It was? What was?
那项研究
The study.
谢谢你
Thank you.
不客气
You're welcome.
詹姆斯
James
出租车两分钟后到
the taxi will be here in two minutes.
哦，干得好，亲
Oh, well done, darling.
我们在街角跟他会合
We'll meet him on the corner.
比利时
Belgium.
哦，谢谢你们
Well, thank you.
呃…两天，是不是？
Two days, isn't it?
- 我们会打电话给你  - 就我而言…
- We'll call you. - I, for one,
永远不会相信上帝跟宇宙玩骰子
will never believe that God plays dice with the universe.
我们在浪费时间
We're wasting time.
来吧，该发球了
Come on, serve already.
真荒谬
That's ridiculous.
你怎么可能浪费不存在的东西？
How can you waste something that doesn't exist?
什么，时间不存在？
What, time doesn't exist?
从何时开始的？
Since when?
我哪儿知道
I wouldn't know.
要是时间不存在，那就没有“何时”了
If time doesn't exist, then there is no "when."
你听见了，李卜克内西？
You hear, Liebitzrecht?
又一个疯狂理论
Another crazy theory.
那就告诉我确切的时间，现在
Then tell me the correct time, now.
看见没？你做不到
You see? You can't.
因为当你告诉我的同时
Because as you're telling me
未来已经变成了过去
the future has already become the past.
因此，没有现在
Therefore, there is no present.
因此，时间不存在
Therefore, time doesn't exist!
现在你的球拍不存在了
Now your racket doesn't exist.
怎么？
Yes?
你是阿尔伯特·爱因斯坦
You're Albert Einstein.
谢谢你
Thank you.
我可以说我是你的超级大粉丝吗？
May I say what a great fan I am of yours?
谢谢你
Thank you.
你写的那个光被地心引力弯曲的东西…
That thing you wrote about light being bent by gravitation
还有整个相对论的东西…哎哟
and the whole relativity thing? Man...
那可真是…
that is...
摇滚
jiving.
我还在努力想把它搞清楚
I'm still trying to figure it out.
我也是
Me, too.
呃，有什么事吗，您是…
Uh, can I help you, Mr....?
沃尔特斯，艾德·沃尔特斯
Walters, Ed Walters.
其实，我在找一位凯瑟琳·博伊德
actually, I was looking for a Catherine Boyd.
我一定是搞错地址了
I must have the wrong address.
抱歉打扰你了，先生
I'm sorry to bother you, sir.
哦，凯瑟琳是我的外甥女
Oh, Catherine's my niece.
她是你外甥女？
She's your niece?
我不能有外甥女吗？
I can't have a niece?
哇，那么你就是她的舅舅了
Well, that would make you her uncle.
这样合情合理，对不对？
It works nicely, doesn't it?
哦，你看，我发现了这个…
Well, you see, I found this...
她的表在我的修车厂，呃…
watch of hers at my garage, and, uh...
哦，谢谢你，我会让她拿到的
Oh, thank you. I'll see that she gets it.
其实，我是希望能个人把它还给她
Actually, I was hoping to return it to her personally.
为什么？
Why?
咱们这么说吧，这样会…
Let's just say it would...
…对她的未来有益处
be beneficial to her future.
也许你最好还是进来吧，沃尔特斯先生
Perhaps you better come in, Mr. Walters.
沃尔特斯先生，让我来介绍鲍里斯·波多尔斯基 [物理学家]
Mr. Walters, may I present Boris Podolsky
库尔特·哥德尔 [数学家]，内森·李卜克内西 [虚构人物]
Kurt Godel, Nathan Liebitzrecht--
20世纪最伟大的三个头脑
three of the greatest minds of the 20th century
而他们当中，连个灯泡都换不了
and amongst them, they can't change a lightbulb.
爱德华，对不对？
Edward, is it?
是的
Yes.
爱德华是来找凯瑟琳的
Edward has come to pay a call on Catherine.
- 哦，真的  - 好啊
- Oh, really. - That's nice.
好啊，非常好
Nice. Very nice.
我可以替你弄好
I could fix this for you.
哦，非常好
Oh, very nice.
非常好，非常感谢
Very nice. Thank you very much.
哦，那是我的指南针
Oh, that's my compass.
就是这个让我开始了我的工作
This is what got me started in my work.
那么，年轻人
So, young man,
你认为时间存在吗？
do you think time exists?
时间？
Time?
我刚刚在《未来科学》杂志上读到这个
I was just reading about it in Future Science magazine.
- 跟我们说说  - 是说…
- Tell us. - It's...
有两个双胞胎，其中一个以光速坐太空船旅行
There are these twins, and one takes a journey in a spacecraft at the speed of light
另一个则留在地球上
and the other one stays on Earth.
嗯，太空旅行的这个双胞胎几年后回到地球
Well, the twin that travels into space comes back years later
他还年轻
and he's young.
而留在地球的这一个
And the one who stayed on Earth,
到这个时候，就很老了
by this time, is very old.
那么，那么你们认为哪个更幸福？
So, so, which one do you think is happier?
年轻的那个
The young one.
对对，对
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
不，是留在后面的那个
No. The one that stayed behind.
为什么？
Why?
因为他有过充实的人生，而且…
Because he's had a full life and...
他经历过，而且爱过痛过，还有…
he's had experiences and love and pain
他有家人和朋友
he has a family and friends.
而那个离开了的
And the one who left,
嗯，时间只是流逝了
well, time has just passed.
对
Yeah.
这个好，不是吗？
This is good, no?
对
Yeah.
告诉我们，你的专业领域是什么？
Tell us, what is your field of expertise?
我的工作？
My job?
我是个…我是个汽车机修工
I'm a... I'm an auto mechanic.
看看合众国，坐着你的雪佛兰，对吧 [德语]？
See the U.S.A. In your Chevrolet, ja?
爱德华，你对重力有何了解？
Edward, what do you know about gravity?
重力？
Gravity?
对
Yeah.
我们有个小小的重力问题
We have a little gravity problem.
拜托要小心，爱德华
Please be careful, Edward.
- 慢慢来  - 好，好
- Take it easy. - Ya, ya.
那么，你对我们凯瑟琳有何想法，沃尔特斯先生？
So, what do you think of our Catherine, Mr. Walters?
我认为她好极了
I think she's wonderful.
好极了的三次方
Wonderful to the power of three.
什么三次方？是十次方
What power of three? To the power of ten!
我们全都爱她
We all love her.
她订婚了，你知道
She's engaged, you know.
对，我知道，我看见戒指了
Yeah, I know. I saw the ring.
他是实验心理学教授
He's a professor of experimental psychology
詹姆斯，呃…
James, uh...
- 莫兰德  - 老鼠男
- Morland. - The rat man.
你知道他做什么吗？
You know what he does?
他把电极放在老鼠的生殖器上
He puts electrodes on the genitals of the rats.
总有一天，我要这样对付他
Some day, I do that to him.
啊，我们把球拍扔起来打小鸟
Ah, we threw the racket up to get the birdie.
我们把哥德尔的手杖扔上去够球拍
We threw Godel's cane up there to get the racket.
我把波多尔斯基的高尔夫球杆扔上去
I threw Podolsky's golf club up there
为了跟他扯平
to get even with him.
下一步我们正要把哥德尔扔上去
We're going to throw Godel up there next.
对
Yeah.
这是一棵恶毒的树
It's a vicious tree.
爱德华 爱德华
Edward, Edward
你凭什么认为她跟你在一起会更好？
what makes you think that she would be better off with you?
我不知道，只是一种感觉
I don't know. Just a feeling.
一种感觉？
A feeling?
什么样的感觉？
What kind of feeling?
这话说起来疯狂
This is going to sound crazy.
- 没关系  - 不不
- That's all right. - No, no.
你可以告诉我们，我们这几个都有些疯狂
You can tell us. We are all a little crazy here.
哦，她来到修车厂的时候…
Well, when she came in the garage...
就好像是一切都慢下来了，还变得非常清晰
it was like everything slowed down, and got very clear.
就好像你在磨凸轮轴的时候
It's like when you're milling a camshaft
或者是在弯道上正撞向挡泥板
or grinding down the curve on a fender.
而就在你正做着的时候
A-A-And as you're doing it,
你就是知道一切都会完美运作
you just know everything is going to work out perfect.
每一件东西都会是合适的
Everything's going to fit.
你知道吧？
You know?
你曾有过那种感觉吗？
You ever have that feeling?
对，有一次，在1905年
Yeah, one time in 1905.
当心，当心啊
Watch out. Watch out now!
沃尔特斯先生，你还好吗？
Mr. Walters, are you all right?
那个重力…真是个杀手
That gravity-- it's a killer.
班伯格先生，我不知道你认为我能做什么
Mr. Bamberger, I don't know what it is you think I can do.
我…我正在完成我的论文
I'm finishing my thesis.
我替我舅舅阿尔伯特做些行政工作
I do some administrative work for my Uncle Albert...
可是他很喜欢你，他们都是
but he adores you. They all do.
他们会听你的
They'll listen to you.
不不不，坐这里
No, no, no, sit here.
全面感受一下
Get the full effect.
拜托
Please.
凯瑟琳，我知道我资助了高等进修学院
Catherine, I know I funded the Institute for Advanced Study...
作为一个纯粹想法的场所
...as a place for pure thought...
可是…下周的研讨会
but... but... the symposium next week...
是我们最后的机会
it's our last chance.
我的会计们都围着我
My accountants are all over me.
坐近一点
Sit a little closer.
告诉你舅舅我们需要某种东西
Tell your uncle we need something...
一项新泽西的新发明
a new invention for New Jersey--
一件可以在这里买到的东西
something that can be... bought here
一件可以在这里制造的东西
something that can be made here
一件可以在这里发射的东西
something that can be launched from here.
这对于学院很重要
It's important for the institute.
高保真音响
Stereo hi-fidelity.
♪ 在某个与世隔绝的约会地点
♪ In some secluded rendezvous
斯派克·琼斯
Spike Jones!
挪近一点
Move a little closer.
声音好像他就在这里
It sounds like he's right here
像是你可以伸手触碰他
like you could reach out and touch him.
或者扇他耳光
Or slap him.
你以每平方秒32英尺的加速度被吸引到地球上
You were attracted to the earth at 32 feet per second per second.
我相信是的
I believe it.
啊，多么美丽的一天
Ah, such a beautiful day.
来吧，我们去找凯瑟琳
Come, we'll find Catherine
你把表给她
and you'll give her the watch.
看看这个
Look at this.
你知道…
You know...
我在瑞士做专利书记员的时候
when I was a patent clerk in Switzerland
我曾经想知道宇宙会是什么样的…
I used to wonder what the universe would look like
…如果我以光速旅行…
if I was traveling at the speed of light...
…在一辆摩托车上
on a motorcycle.
哈罗，爱因斯坦教授
Hello, professor Einstein!
你好吗，博士？
How you doing, doc?
好，很好
Good. Very good.
我一直想要一辆敞篷车
I always wanted a convertible.
哇呼
Wahoo!
[ 德语 ]
什么？
What?
再快点 再快点
Faster. Faster.
好的，抓紧了，博士
Okay, hang on, doc.
哇呼
Wahoo!
（潘恩行为研究所）
莫兰德
Morland!
求你
Please...
救命…救命
Help... help!
詹姆斯
James...
啊，教授
Ah, professor.
我正在找凯瑟琳，她在这里吗？
I was looking for Catherine. Is she here?
不，没在，不过我总是很高兴你来的
No. No, but I'm glad you've come anyway.
莫兰德博士
Dr. Morland!
- 我再也不做你的实验了  - 是不是应该有人帮帮这人？
- I'm not going to do your test anymore! - Shouldn't somebody help this guy?
哦，他没事
Oh, he's all right.
这是一个时间剥夺实验
It's a time deprivation experiment.
来吧，看一看
Go on. Have a look.
这个完全出自《火星人吃了我的大脑》
This is right out of Martians Ate My Brain.
你读过这个故事吗？
Have you ever read that story?
我是不是认识你？
Don't I know you?
这是我的朋友爱德华
This is my friend Edward.
我们一起在做一项研究
We're working on something together.
真的吗？是什么？
Really? What?
远距离的吸引力
Attraction at a distance.
哦…我们，呃…
Well... shall we, uh...
去看一下那个…呃…
go and have a look at the, uh...
还有，呃，请不要触摸任何东西，好吗？
and, uh, please, don't touch anything, will you?
我来给你们展示我以前说过的老鼠
Let me show you the mouse I was talking about.
他就在这里
He's just around here.
好了，这只老鼠已经学会
Now, the mouse has learned
红色操纵杆会给他的大脑一个电刺激
that the red lever will give him an electrical stimulus in the brain
有些类似于性高潮
that's something akin to sexual climax
而蓝色操纵杆会分发给他食物
and the blue lever will dispense him food.
现在，这里这只已经三天没吃东西了
Now, this one here hasn't eaten for three days.
那边
There.
好了，他为什么那样做呢？
Now, why would he do that?
呃…失陪一下，好吗？
Uh... excuse me a moment, will you?
格雷琴，你可以…呃
Gretchen, would you, um...
这还蛮稀奇的
that's curious.
小隔间里的那个家伙那么快就冷静下来了
That fellow in the booth calmed down so quickly.
对，有意思，是吧？
Yes. Funny, huh?
你的手表呢？
Where's your watch?
啊？
Huh?
你原先戴着一块腕表
You were wearing a wristwatch.
哦，我琢磨着既然时间不存在…
Well, I figured since time doesn't exist--
谁还需要表呢？
who needs a watch?
这一趟非常出色 [德语]
That was ausgezeichnet.
非常感谢
Thank you very much.
您完全不必客气
You're very welcome.
下次我带上我的护目镜，如何？
Next time I bring my goggles, ja?
好的，博士
All right, doc.
[ 哼“第13号小夜曲”]
啊，凯瑟琳
Ah, Catherine...
修车厂
The garage.
他很了不起，你舅舅
He's quite a guy, your uncle.
对，他…他…
Yes, he... he...
你认识他吗？
Do you know him?
我交游广泛
I get around.
你带他坐那玩意儿？
Did you take him on that thing?
嗯哼
Uh-huh.
你带阿尔伯特·爱因斯坦坐摩托车兜风？
You took Albert Einstein for a ride on a motorcycle?
嗯哼
Uh-huh.
- 噢，可再也别那么干了  - 为什么？
- Well, don't ever do that again. - Why not?
因为他可能会被害死
Because he could've been killed.
他爱得不行
He loved it.
他喊“哇呼”呢
He went "wahoo."
哇呼？
Wahoo?
他上次喊“哇呼”是什么时候？
When was the last time he went "wahoo"?
哦，我肯定不知道
Well, I'm sure I don't know.
你上次喊“哇呼”是什么时候？
When was the last time you went "wahoo"?
哦，我肯定不知道
Well, I'm sure I don't know.
想…想搭个车吗？
Want a... want a lift?
坐那个？
On that?
不
No.
[学马龙·白兰度]：来吧，又会怎么样呢？你死去一点点罢了
[like Marlon Brando]: Come on, what could happen? So you die a little.
喂，帮我一下，好吗？
Hey, help me out, will you?
我有点紧张
I'm a little nervous.
哦，真的吗？为什么？
Oh, really? Why?
我正在努力琢磨一个最好的办法邀请你吃晚饭
I'm trying to figure out the best way to ask you to dinner.
呃…未请教…
Uh... mister...
沃尔特斯，艾德
Walters. Ed.
对
Right.
我肯定你是个很好的人
I'm sure you're a very nice person
而且我很高兴知道我未来的汽车安全…
and I'm happy to know that my future automotive safety
掌握在你那双巨大、很有能力的手中
is in your large, very capable hands
但我…我真的应该走那边，所以…
but I-I really should be going that way, so...
再见
good-bye.
哦，那么说晚饭是谈不上了
Well, then dinner's out of the question.
对
Yeah.
那么我应该给你这个
So I should give you this.
你找到了它
You found it.
你落下了它
You left it.
你修好了它
You fixed it.
我擦亮了它
I polished it.
谢谢你
Thank you.
我还拧紧了螺丝
And I tightened the screws.
我能感觉到
I can feel that.
它很漂亮
It's very pretty.
以前是我父亲的
It was my father's.
我以为我把它弄丢了
I thought I'd lost it.
谢谢你
Thank you.
不客气
You're welcome.
呃…如果我之前太唐突，我很抱歉
Um...I'm sorry if I was abrupt before.
没问题
No problem.
怎么？
What?
惊人
Astonishing.
一个明白无误的化学反应
An unmistakable chemical reaction.
怎么？
What?
马龙·白兰度
Marlon Brando.
也许不是
Maybe not.
那么，詹姆斯？
So, James?
什么？
Yes?
会是哪里呢？
Where is it to be?
什么是哪里，邓肯？
Where is what to be, Duncan?
蜜月，老兄，蜜月
The honeymoon, man, the honeymoon.
你们这对爱情鸟决定了哪里？
What have you two lovebirds decided on?
呃，这个我们还没怎么好好讨论过
Uh, well, we haven't really discussed it much.
呣，不过我想去比属刚果的伊图里森林
Um, though I was thinking the Ituri forest in the Belgian Congo.
伊图里森林，太好了
The Ituri forest. Excellent.
恩布提定居点附近有个俾格米人村落
There's a pygmy village near the Embouti settlement.
你知道那里，是不是，邓肯？
You know it, don't you, Duncan?
对啊，那里真是引人入胜
Yes, it's fascinating.
如果你愿意的话，可以说是一个完整的俾格米人套餐
Sort of a complete pygmy package if you'd like.
有好客之心，野猪烧烤
There's hospitality heart, wild boar roast
你在河里洗浴，部落仪式…
you wash in the river, tribal rituals...
诸如此类的事情
that sort of a thing.
就像成为部落的一员，真的
It's like being one of the tribe, really.
这是一生难得的机会
It's the opportunity of a lifetime.
我喜欢
I like it.
我想的…更多是顺着百万个吻在你的肌肤上的思路
I was thinking more along the lines of a million kisses on your skin.
你说什么，花栗鼠？
I beg your pardon, chimpmunk?
毛伊岛上，有一些天然滑梯
On Maui they have these natural slides
由火山喷发的黑曜石形成
formed from these volcanic eruptions of obsidian
你爬上去
and you go climbing up
然后你滑下一百英尺
and then you go sliding down a hundred feet
进入他们所谓的七圣池
into what they call the Seven Sacred Pools.
那里的水充满二氧化碳气体
And the water is so aerated
感觉就像是百万个吻在你的肌肤上
that it feels like a million kisses on your skin
或者像一条巨大的舌头舔着你的全身
or like an enormous tongue just licking your entire body.
迪恩，你还记得我们谈过资金的事吗？
Dean, do you remember we were talking about the funding?
黑曜石滑梯和巨大的舔舌？
Obsidian slides and great licking tongues?
我的天，他是整个部门的头头
My god, he's the head of the whole department.
- 詹姆斯？  - 嗯？
- James? - Hmm?
你喜欢百万个吻在你的肌肤上吗？
How would you like a million kisses on your skin?
什么？
What?
我们进行自己的原始仪式怎样？就在这里
What if we have our own primitive ritual right here.
你疯了吗？
Have you gone mad?!
你在干什么？
What are you doing?!
你不爱我
You don't love me.
什么，就因为我不愿意在晚宴当中跟你做爱？
What, because I won't make love to you in the middle of some dinner party?
凯瑟琳，你怎么能说这种话？
Catherine, how can you say such a thing?
你知道我爱你超过一切
You know I love you more than anything.
你是我的小鼠花栗，不是吗？
You're my little munchkin, aren't you?
我不知道，詹姆斯，我是吗？
I don't know, James. Am I?
你当然是啦
But of course you are.
我的小小小鼠花栗
My little munchy munchkin.
你看
Look
我本打算晚点再告诉你的
I wasn't going to tell you this till later
不过你记得我跟你说过的那个惊喜吗？
but you remember that surprise I told you about?
不
No.
那些卡片，那些颜色卡片
The cards. The color cards.
对
Yes.
好了，等我们度完蜜月回家
Well, when we come home from our honeymoon
我们会有一个家可以回
we're going to have a home to come home to.
在斯坦福
In Stanford.
正教授，应用心理学系，还有…
Full professor. Department of Applied Psychology. And...
随之而来的是我们自己的小鼠花栗窝
...it comes with its own little munchkin nest.
而且你已经挑选了颜色
And you already picked out the color.
藻绿
Algae.
这是个颜色？
This is a color?
而且还有足够的房间给孩子们
And there'll be plenty of room for the children.
孩子们
Children...
詹姆斯说让他们之间隔三年半
James says that spacing them three and a half years apart
对他们的心智发展是最理想的
is optimal for their mental development.
可你的心智发展怎么办？
But what about your mental development?
什么？
What?
你的研究
Your research.
我不知道
I don't know.
有时候我想知道自己当母亲会不会比不上…
Sometimes I wonder if I wouldn't be a better mother
当一个机修工…数学家
than a mechanic... mathematician.
凯瑟琳
Catherine...
你父亲请求我照顾你的时候
when your father asked me to care for you
我试过告诉他
I tried to tell him that...
我所知道的东西在现实世界里不太有用
the things I know are not very useful in the real world.
这就是为什么我很幸运有詹姆斯
And that's why I'm so lucky that I have James.
我们有共同的目标和利益
We have common goals and interests.
他聪明，有条理，是个计划者
He's brilliant, organized, a planner.
我发现他很有启发性
I find him very stimulating.
在智力方面
Intellectually.
对，可爱情呢，凯瑟琳？
Yeah, but what about love, Catherine?
什么？
What?!
我说这一切何时发生…
I said when does this all happen--
这种美妙的有组织的生活？
this wonderful, organized life?
在九月份
In September.
他们说斯坦福很美丽
They say Stanford is beautiful.
那是他们说的
That's what they say.
这是我一生中最幸福的日子
This is the happiest day of my entire life.
别担心，宝贝 [德语]
Don't worry, liebchen.
会解决的
It will work out.
[ 德语]
我保证
I promise.
♪ 有个女孩名叫苏
♪ Got a gal named Sue
♪ 她知道该怎么办…
♪ She knows just what to do...
我狂爱这首歌
I'm crazy about this song.
把他考倒了
Get him.
你是什么呢，波多尔斯基，爵士乐迷？
What are you, Podolsky, a hep cat?
不，我是美国人
No. I'm an American.
哦…那到底是什么歌呢
Oh... so what is it,
爵士乐迷美国人先生？
Mr. hep cat American?
我知道，是…是…
I know. It's a... it's a...
当心
Look out!
学些开车，老天在上
Learn to drive for God's sake!
他们应该让人先通过考试再允许他们开车
They should make people pass a test before they let them drive!
你是得通过考试啊
You had to pass a test.
不然你怎么拿到驾照？
How else could you get a license?
- 驾照？  - 我知道了
- A license? - I got it.
是《什锦水果》还是锦果？
It's "tutti frutti" or hutti?
安静！
Quiet!
你今天是怎么回事，阿尔伯特？
What is wrong with you today, Albert?
凯瑟琳…
Catherine--
她应该多找些乐子
she should be having more fun.
她需要的是一个年轻人
What she needs is a young man.
她应该出去，去跳舞…
She should go out, go dancing...
来点“schtupping” [性爱]
A little schtupping.
得了吧
GODEL:Come on.
内森，拜托
Nathan, please.
她以为“schtupping”是巴伐利亚的一个镇子呢
PODOLSKY: She thinks schtupping is a town in Bavaria.
你带我们去哪里，阿尔伯特？
Where are you taking us, Albert?
哦，小伙子们，你们喜欢来一辆敞篷车吗？
Well, boys, how would you like to have a convertible?
- 妙啊！  - 妙啊！
- Excellent! - Excellent.
完美
Perfect.
哦，漂亮
Oh, beautiful.
先生？
Sir?
这装潢很漂亮
It's very nice upholstery.
你是阿尔伯特·爱因斯坦
You're Albert Einstein.
E = mc²
E = mc squared.
我希望如此
I hope so.
告诉我，这车从工厂里出来就是这样子？
Tell me, this comes from the factory like this?
哦，不不不，全是订做的
Oh, no, no. It's all custom.
我不敢相信…在我的修车厂
I can't believe it--in my garage.
这可真是荣幸
This is a real honor.
弗兰基，这是爱因斯坦教授
Frankie, this is Professor Einstein,
世界上最聪明的人
the smartest person in the world.
他们怎么样了？
How they hanging?
爱德华！
Edward!
嘿，博士
Hey, doc.
爱德华
Edward.
它在那里
There it is.
你怎么想？有可能吗？
What do you think? Is it possible?
当然，任何事都有可能
Sure. Anything's possible.
他想把那车变成这个…
He wants to turn that into this...
敞篷车
Convertible.
没问题
No problem.
你是说全面护理吗，教授？
You were talking about the full treatment, Professor?
对对 [德语]，从头到尾
Ja, ja. The whole ball of wax.
波多尔斯基，住手
Podolsky, stop that.
好的，那么我们把顶部切掉
Okay, so we chop the top,
做一个改进的机头和装甲…
do a modified nose and deck...
填充起来
Fill and block.
法式褶边和滚边在里面
French tuck and roll on the inside.
前面用达格材料？
Dago the front?
就要一点
Just a touch.
- 引擎四套件管  - 对
- Quad barrels for the mill. - Yeah.
大师工具箱
A master kit.
热盘管
Hot coil.
针刺排气
Stinger exhaust.
高镍铬
High nickel chrome.
听着不错吧？
Sound good?
像是莫扎特
Like Mozart.
你看，我记得这里有一家冰淇淋商店
You know, I recall here someplace is an ice cream parlor.
来吧，我们买一个去
Come, we get a scoop.
博士，其实，是这边
Doc, actually, it's this way.
- 哦，对  - 可以吗？
- Oh, yeah. - Is it all right?
没事，去吧
Yeah, go, go.
非常感谢
Thank you very much.
- 当然  - 当然
- Sure. - Sure.
我1933年第一次到这里的时候
When I first arrived here in 1933,
我去买了一个这种三球冰淇淋
I went and bought one of these triple scoops.
什么口味的？
What flavor?
薄荷
Peppermint.
你看
You see?
这是个好问题
This is a good question.
“什么口味的”
"What flavor?"
简单，具体，而且有一个答案
Simple, specific, and it has an answer.
你读了好多科幻小说
You read a lot of science fiction.
告诉我，你认为他们究竟会不会…
Tell me, do you think they'll ever find...
…在宇宙某处找到智慧生命？
...intelligent life anywhere in the universe?
他们仍然在地球这里寻找智慧生命呢
They're still looking for intelligent life here on Earth.
你看，凯瑟琳…她是个有才华的数学家
You know, Catherine-- she's a brilliant mathematician
但她缺乏自信
but she lacks confidence.
她认为她对世界的贡献…
She thinks her contribution to the world...
…将通过她的孩子达成
...will be through her children.
她有一个发疯的想法
She has this crazy idea
如果她嫁给一个知识分子
that if she marries an intellectual
她就会生下天才儿童等等之类
she will have genius children or something like that.
凯瑟琳，她太聪明了不该那样
Catherine-- she's too smart for that.
哦，她这里太聪明
Oh, she's too smart here.
但不是这里
But not here.
她需要的是跟你这样的人出去
What she needs is to go out with someone like you.
问题在于
The problem is
她永远也不会跟你这样的人出去
she would never go out with someone like you.
这个容易
That's easy.
只要把你的大脑借给我几天
Just lend me your brain for a couple of days.
什么？
What?
你跟我想的是一回事吗？
Are you thinking what I am thinking?
这个发生的机会有多大？
What would be the odds of that happening?
还是不对
It's still not right.
什么？
What?
他看来不像是个科学家
He doesn't look like a scientist.
那么，再说说计划是怎样的，博士？
So, what's the plan again, doc?
给，试试这个
Here, try this.
计划是我们谈论科学
The plan is we talk science.
我们弄些东西吃
So we have something to eat.
我们喝点杜松子酒
We drink some schnapps.
我们谈谈人生
And we talk about life.
我认为这样太时髦了
I think it's too fashionable.
对对
Yeah, yeah.
来…
Here--
来，拿上，有件外套
Here, take some. There's a coat.
等等，等等
Wait, wait.
内森，你的羊毛衫
Nathan, your cardigan.
要是她问我问题我怎么办？
What do I do if she asks me a question?
她问你问题…
She asks you a question...
给…你就假装吸烟斗
here-- you pretend to smoke a pipe.
然后你说
And then you say,
“有趣的概念”
"Interesting concept."
别担心
Don't worry.
我们会转移话题的
We'll change the subject.
转移话题？
Change the subject?
你懂的，比如说足球
You know, like in football.
我们会进行干扰
We'll run interference.
现在…
And now...
这是一条领带
this is a tie.
给…这个可以把你的裤子系住
Here-- this will hold up your pants.
不错，是吧？
Good, huh?
- 对  - 对
- Yeah. - Yeah.
他看起来像是个法国印象派艺术家
He looks like a French impressionist.
对对
Yeah, yeah.
…这个核构型
...the nuclear configuration
由核哈密顿量的期望值给出
given by the expectation value of the nuclear Hamiltonian,
在“M”中子的状态下…
in a state with "M" neutrons...
- 对  - 对
- Yeah. - Yeah.
…就会引发，如果熔合状态的能量低于那个能量…
...Will occur if the energy of the fuse state is lower than the energy of...
- 对  - 对
- Yeah. - Yeah.
我们的任务，是看看由交互作用的哈密顿量支配的动力
Our task is to see if the dynamics dictated by the interaction Hamiltonian
是否产生足够快速的反应
generates a sufficiently rapid reaction
使冷聚变动力发动机成为可能
to make cold fusion-powered engines feasible.
- 不错  - 嗯哼  - 所以，让…
- Good. - Uh-huh. - So, let...
哈罗
Hello.
哈罗，亲爱的 [德语]
Hello, liebchen.
所以，我们有
So, we have here
E除以C的平方
E over C squared.
是E的平方
It's E squared.
减去E平方除以B
Minus E squared over B
- 对  - 减去V (X)
- Ya. - minus V of X.
呃，怎么回事？
Uh, what's going on?
看起来我们这位朋友爱德华…
It seems our friend Edward here...
一直对我们深藏不露
...has been holding out on us.
除了是一名很不错的汽车机修工
In addition to being a very fine automotive mechanic
他在物理学方面也算得上是个神童
he is also in physics something of a wunderkind.
一个神童
A wunderkind.
我，我有了一个想法
I, I had this idea.
我跟博士谈了谈
I ran it by the doc
我们一起研究了一下
and we worked on it together
大家都认为这想法不太坏
and everybody thought it wasn't so bad.
啥！“不太坏”？
So! "It wasn't so bad."
简直是惊人
It was astonishing.
非常具有革新性
Very innovative.
哦，我可以听听是什么吗？
Well, do I get to hear what it is?
我想出了怎么建造一台核动力空间飞船引擎，个人想法
I figured out how to build a nuclear-powered spacecraft engine, I think.
一台核聚变引擎
A fusion engine.
一台啥？
A what?!
给恒星烧燃料的过程
The process that fuels the stars.
我们要把它放进一个瓶子里
We're going to put it in a bottle.
冷聚变
Cold fusion.
这可大费脑力了
It's mind-boggling.
他是个机修工
He's a mechanic.
我曾经是个专利局的办事员
I was a clerk in a patent office.
法拉第曾经当过木匠
Faraday was a carpenter.
艾萨克·牛顿曾经当过保险推销员
Isaac Newton was an insurance salesman.
核聚变
Fusion.
真的吗？
Really?
噢，你穿的什么啊？
Well, what are you wearing?
他穿什么有什么区别吗？
What difference does it make what he is wearing?
一台核动力空间飞船
A nuclear-powered spacecraft.
哇，这对于新泽西太合适了
Well, that's perfect for New Jersey.
- 新泽西？  - 新泽西？
- New Jersey? - New Jersey?
那个研讨会
The symposium.
我想你们没有写好这方面的论文吧
I don't suppose you have a paper on this.
论文？
Paper?
不不，你看
No, no, you see,
还有一些特定的细节…
there are certain details...
- 我们必须检查拼写…  - 拼写，对
- We must check the spelling. - Spelling, right.
我们能把它准备好
We could have it ready.
- 你们能吗？  - 对，当然
- You could?  - Yeah. Sure.
我们不能吗？
Couldn't we?
对，我们能
Ja, we could.
研讨会是什么时候？
When is the symposium?
四月一号
April 1.
五天
Five days.
这不成问题
That's not a problem.
哦，这可太好了
Oh, this is great!
班伯格会激动的
Bamberger will be thrilled.
我真是…
I am
感激不尽
very grateful.
这事情是多么的…
This is so...
…宏大，真的
huge, really.
艾萨克·牛顿没有当过保险推销员
Isaac Newton was not an insurance salesman.
咋啦？
W-what?
伙子们，我们的小实验
Boys, our little experiment
刚刚跃迁到了一个更高的能量层
has just jumped to a higher energy level.
除以X…
Over X...
减Y到X加Y…
minus Y to the X + Y...
减去Y到X…
Minus Y to the X...
那是什么语言，火星语？
What language is that, Martian?
等等，等一下，等等
Wait, wait a minute, wait.
你没有改换什么东西，对吧？
You're not changing anything, are you?
没有
No.
那是在闹哪样？
Well, what's all that?
没啥
Nothing.
好吧，拿好你的解剖刀
All right, grab your scalpel.
咱们开刀了
Let's operate.
我不敢相信！
I don't believe it!
爱因斯坦的车！
Einstein's car!
我们这趟要是做好了，艾迪伙计
We do this right, Eddie boy,
我们就会有全新的客户群体了
we're going to have a whole new clientele!
（物理学与空间 国际研讨会）
欢迎来到第一届国际物理学研讨会
Welcome to the first international physics symposium
旨在汇集最优秀的头脑
designed to bring together the very best minds.
时候到了，爱德华
It's time, Edward.
这是聚集了最大规模的科学…
Now, this is the largest gathering of the scientific...
我做不了这个
I can't do this.
为什么？因为你害怕焦虑而不舒服吗？
Why? Because you're sick with fear and anxiety?
世界上99%的人每天早上醒来都如此
99% Of the world wakes up like this every morning.
每天早上
Every morning.
对，每天早上
Yeah, every morning.
爱德华，只要记住…
Edward, just remember
…你为什么要做这件事
...why you are doing this.
很多神秘之事我们迄今为止，只…
Many of the mysteries that we, until now, only...
她都不在这里
She's not even here.
你看，我是说，倒不是他从未表现出任何…
You know, I mean it's not as if he's even ever shown any signs of
正常智力的迹象
…normal intelligence.
想想这个…核聚变
Think of that--nuclear fusion.
对，我是说我估计这种事情也是有的
Ya, I mean I suppose these things happen.
天才白痴…你懂的
Idiot savant-- you know,
一名精神病患象棋下得极好
a mental patient plays perfect chess
一个阿拉巴马的九岁孩子突然开口吟诗作对
a nine-year-old from Alabama suddenly starts speaking in iambic pentameter.
詹姆斯，人都挤满了
James, it's packed!
为我们的议程开场，递交其论文…
To open our program here, delivering his paper
标题为“冷聚变驱动探索范式”的
entitled "Cold Fusion-Powered Exploration Paradigms"
就是我们的爱德华·沃尔特斯
is our very own Edward Walters.
爱德华·沃尔特斯
Edward Walters.
沃尔特斯博士？
Dr. Walters?
博士…
Doctor...?
你还好吗，沃尔特斯博士？
Are you all right, Dr. Walters?
艾德
Ed.
艾德？
Ed?
艾德
Ed.
不不
No, no
是P方除以N，不是N方除以P
it's P squared over N, not N squared over P.
她都不在这里
She's not even here.
要是她嫁给一个天才，她会生个天才儿童
If she marries a genius, she'll have genius children.
做点什么
Do something.
我是在做点什么，可是没有帮助
I am doing something, but it's not helpful.
也不愉快
Or pleasant.
一种核动力空间飞船
A nuclear-powered spacecraft.
出类拔萃的同行们…
Distinguished colleagues...
嘉宾们…
honored guests...
爱德华，记住你为什么要做这件事
Edward, just remember why you are doing this.
生活中的任何旅程…
Any journey in life...
如果不是出于人类的原因，带着理解和爱…
if not done for human reasons, with understanding and love...
这不是我们写的论文
This is not the paper we wrote.
嘘
Shh!
- …就会非常空洞和孤单  - 听
- ... would be a very empty and lonely one. - Listen.
看看
And look.
有些东西值得记住，因为…
Something worth remembering, since...
核动力飞船也许很快就能…
...nuclear-powered spacecraft may soon
…让旅行至宇宙边缘再返回的古老梦想…
make the ancient dream of traveling to the edge of the universe and back...
…成为现实
a reality.
那种动力的来源
The source of that power
就是恒星的燃料来源其本身，而且…
is the very source that fuels the stars themselves and...
这样做…
in doing so...
给我们的想象力和梦想加注了燃料
…fuels our imagination and our dreams.
让我们假设…
Let us suppose
V (X)是穿透潜能的标准界限
that V of X is the standard barrier of penetration potential
还有其尺寸以及原子核函数
and that size... and nuclear ...function...
然后按照常规，减去I-H-R-D sin（D-T）等于
then, as usual, minus I-H-R-D sine D-T equals
减掉D平方
minus D squared
ψ（D-X）平方
psi D-X squared
加上V (X)
plus V of X.
- 精彩  - 精彩
- Bravo. - Bravo.
真是个马戏团
What a circus!
好像科学分析还不够让人麻木似的
As if the scientific analysis wasn't mind-numbing enough
那些有关人类心灵的伤感话语是在搞什么？
what was all that mush about the human heart?
你不懂是因为你不是物理学家
You didn't understand that because you're not a physicist.
对，不过我们要记住，亲
Yeah, well, let's remember, darling,
直到最近之前他也不是
neither was he until recently.
你有没有注意到他指甲里还有润滑油？
Did you notice he still had grease under his fingernails?
爱德华，恭喜
Edward, congratulations.
敬天才
To genius.
敬核聚变
To fusion.
敬心灵
To the heart.
啊，哦，所以你从未上过大学
Ah, oh, so you never went to college.
我几乎没读完高中
I barely finished high school.
我一直在拆解车子
I was always taking apart some car.
然而，你对理论的把握如此惊人
And yet, you have such an amazing grasp of theory.
你知道吗，我相信你用了德布罗利公式
Do you know, I believe that you used Debrawley's formula
来计算导波的长度
for the length of the pilot wave.
他当然如此啦
Of course he did.
这是出色的一着
It was a brilliant stroke.
没有它我做不到
I couldn't have done without it.
哦！我都忘了
Oh! I forgot that.
等一下你可否，可否提醒我一下
Wait a minute. Could you, could you remind me?
好，嗯，当然
Yeah. Um, sure.
X
（这个公式是杜撰的，大概是以德布罗意为原型）
等于…
equals...
one
加，呃…
plus, uh...
W
W...
X等于1加W
X equals one plus W
立方
cubed...
除
in...
除以Π
over pi.
对对
Right, right.
你能发明它吗？
Can you invert that?
他在哪里？
Where is he?!
那个美少年在哪里？
Where is that beautiful boy?
火箭飞船
Rocket ships.
本垒打，凯瑟琳，本垒打！
Home run, Catherine, home run!
谢谢你，先生
Thank you, sir.
艾德·沃尔特斯，允许我介绍路易斯·班伯格
Ed Walters, may I present Louis Bamberger?
如果他每有一分钱你就有一分钱
If you had a nickel for every nickel he has,
你就会有好多好多钱
you would have a lot of nickels.
荣而又幸，先生
An honor and a pleasure, sir.
新泽西…
New Jersey--
星系间火箭探索的领导者
leader in intergalactic rocket exploration.
这个车牌听起来怎么样？
How does that sound for a license plate?
长
Long.
幽默感
sense of humor.
我爱这个小伙子
I love this boy.
我能把我外甥女偷走一会儿吗，劳驾？
May I steal my niece for one minute, please?
哦，其实我们正要走
Uh, well, actually, we were just about to leave.
就一会儿，拜托
Just for one moment, please.
- 我需要点空气  - 哦…
- I need some air. - Well...
詹姆斯，老鼠业务怎么一样了？
James, how is the rat business?
呣，这个，我现在的实验对象其实是学生
Um, well, it's really students that I'm experimenting on now.
我的天，那些迷宫一定很大
My god, the mazes must be enormous.
绿色，黑色，红色
Green, black, red.
看看
Look at that.
这就像是一次有了四支笔
It's like having four pens in one.
活在这个时代多么令人激动啊
What an exciting time to be alive.
路易斯，我们需要谈一谈
Louis, we need to have a talk.
说的是我能理解的东西，对吗？
This is going to be something I understand, isn't it?
- 对对  - 我是说我听不懂你跟我说的东西
- Yeah, yeah. - I mean I don't understand what you say to me.
对，可是你看…
Yes, but you see...
哦，这下好多了
Oh, that's better.
看，凯瑟琳
Look, Catherine.
看看星星，看看天空
Look at the stars, look at the sky
看看…
look at...
爱德华
Edward.
我们刚才正在谈论星星
We were just talking about the stars.
啊…好了，呼吸够了
Ah... well, enough breathing.
多好的晚上
What a night.
从孩提时以来我就再没见过这样的天空
I haven't see a sky like this since I was a kid.
那是天文学家的领域
That's stargazers' field.
你觉得上面有多少颗星星？
How many stars do you think are up there?
呃，10的12次方，加1
Um, ten to the twelfth, plus one.
你不必那样说
you don't have to say that.
不，真的，人人都很佩服你
No, really, everybody is quite impressed.
你知道为什么彗尾总是远离太阳那面吗？
Do you know why a comet's tail always points away from the sun?
知道
Yes.
我也知道
Me, too.
我的奶奶曾经告诉我
My grandma used to tell me that
星星是啄木鸟在天空中啄洞的地方
stars are where a woodpecker pecked holes in the sky.
她没有那么多科学头脑
She wasn't that scientifically minded.
当我父亲仰望天空时，他并没有真正看到星星
When my father looked at the sky he didn't really see stars.
他说他看见…
He said he saw
巨大的火海和核熔炉
great seas of fire and nuclear furnaces.
他说那就像一场非常暴力的芭蕾舞
He said it was like a very violent ballet
只不过它太小了，谁也看不见
only it was too small for anyone to see.
什么事把詹姆斯给耽搁了？
What is keeping James?
我不知道
I don't know.
他发现了一颗彗星
He discovered a comet.
詹姆斯发现了一颗…？
James discovered a...?
不，我父亲
No. My father.
他们以他的名字给它命名
They named it after him.
博伊德彗星
Boyd's comet.
嗯哼
Mm-hmm.
哦，我的天，那是你
Oh, my god, that's you.
那是你父亲
That's your father.
我…
I...
我刚刚读到那些，在那本…
I was just reading about that in the...
哦，你读过他的著作？
Oh, you've read his works?
哦，一部分吧，那么多本呢
Well, some of them. There are so many.
三本
Three.
三本？真的吗？那个…
Three? Really? There...
感觉好像要多些
it seemed like more.
它们都内容丰富
They're all so action-packed.
内容丰富？
Action-packed?
他在说什么？
What is he saying?
他回来了
He's coming back.
詹姆斯？
James?
不是
No.
呃，我父亲
Uh, my father.
你看，他临死前保证说…
You know, just before he died he promised that...
当那颗彗星回来的时候，他会骑在上面
when the comet came back he'd be riding on it.
就在，呃…
Right, uh....
就在那边
right there.
我认为是在那边，就在仙后座的下方
I think it's there, just below Cassiopeia.
啊，你说得对
Ah, you're right.
他说过他会…
He said he'd be...
…骑在上面俯视下方，确保我没事
...riding on it looking down to make sure I was okay.
那么你怎么样？还好吗？
So, how are you? Are you okay?
凯瑟琳？
Catherine?
凯瑟琳
Catherine!
老鼠男来啦
The rat man cometh.
我…
I...
凯瑟琳？
Catherine?
谁去叫医生
Somebody call a doctor.
阿尔伯特，说句话啊
Albert, say something.
我只是午餐吃了太多knerdler
I just had too many knerdlers for lunch.
我需要我的药
I need my pills.
凯瑟琳，你知道在哪里吧？
Catherine, you know where they are?
在家里
At home.
- 我们走  - 好
- Let's go. - Ya.
爱德华，你开车载我
Edward, you drive me.
对，好的，你…你开车载他回家
Yes, all right, you-you drive him home.
我来收拾你的东西，凯瑟琳
I'll collect your things, Catherine,
回头我在“每日咖啡杯”跟你见面
and I'll see you at the Cafe Day Cup later.
好的 好的
Yes. Yes.
好吗？
Yes?
阿尔伯特，你要我们跟你来吗？
Albert, you want us to come with you?
不不
No, no.
当心
Watch out.
再见，拜托
Good-bye, please.
我们走，我们走
Let's go. Let's go.
等一下
Wait a minute.
我们怎么回家？
How do we get home?
好问题
Good question.
这是个美好的晚上
it's a lovely night.
我们走路
We walk.
哦，看，我找到我的药了
Oh, look, I found my pills.
现在…也许我们可以弄个玻璃杯放进去
Now... maybe we can catch some of this in a glass.
应该让你下车
Should get you out of this.
对，是个好主意
Yeah, that's a good idea.
那边
Over there.
那家咖啡馆，爱德华
That cafe, Edward.
对，这是个…很糟糕的阿尔伯特·爱因斯坦笑话
Yeah, it's a... very bad Albert Einstein joke.
玛丽瓦是他的第一个妻子
Maleva was his first wife.
她跟他离了婚
She divorced him.
对，我生活在这里太多，这里不够多
Yeah, I lived too much here and not enough here.
她有孩子吗？
She have children?
两个男孩
Two boys.
汉斯·阿尔伯特
Hans Albert.
我不在的时候他母亲给他起的名字
His mother named him while I was out of town.
还有爱德华
And Edward.
什么？
Yes?
不，爱德华是另一个男孩的名字
No. Edward was the name of the other boy.
那么，你一定在这里生活过至少两次
Well, you must have lived here at least twice.
爱德华…
Edward...
你一开始是怎么想到原子燃料的？
how did you first think of atomic fuel?
哦，就好像是灵光一现
Well, it just sort of hit me.
是凯斯勒式的一闪还是个偶然？
Was it a Kessler boom or an accident?
因为凯斯勒认为偶然的发现根本不是偶然
Because Kessler believes that accidental discoveries are not accidents at all.
人们会有顿悟和直觉的时刻
That people have moments of insight and intuition
他们已准备好靠他们的经验来认识自己的本来面目
that they're prepared for by their experience to recognize them for what they are.
唠叨
Babbling.
唠叨？
Babbling?
不，你没有唠叨
No, you're not babbling.
要是我有你这样的头脑，我不会停止说话
If I had a mind like yours, I wouldn't stop talking.
我觉得雨在减弱
I think it's letting up.
我觉得她想离开
I think she wants to leave.
她不知道她想要什么
She doesn't know what she wants.
还在下雨
Still raining.
我想你舅舅想要我们…跳舞
I think your uncle wants us... to dance.
哦，好啦
Oh, now,
不要跑题了，艾德
don't be irrelevant, Ed.
你不能从那里走到这里
You can't get from there to here.
为什么？
Why not?
好了，可别告诉我…
Now, don't tell me that...
你这样一个著名的出色科学家
...a famous and brilliant scientist such as yourself
会不知道芝诺佯谬
doesn't know about Zeno's paradox.
提醒我一下
Remind me.
你不能从那边走到这边
You can't get from there to here
因为你总是要覆盖剩下的一半距离
because you always have to cover half the remaining distance.
比如从我到你，我得走一半路
Like, from me to you, I have to cover half of it.
可是，看？我还有一半路要走，所以…
But, see? I still have half of that remaining, so...
我走一半的路，然后…
I cover half that and, um...
那就还有一半的路剩下
there's still half of that left
所以我又走一半的路
so I cover half of that
然后，呃…一半的路
and, uh... half of that
再一半，再一半
and half of that and half of that.
由于有无穷无尽的一半路剩下…
And since there are infinite halves left...
永远也不能到达
can't ever get there.
所以这是怎么发生的？
So how did that happen?
我不知道
I don't know.
这不可能
It's not possible.
詹姆斯
James.
不，是艾德
No. Ed.
詹姆斯，我应该去跟他会合的
James. I was supposed to meet him.
走，走，走，走
Go, go, go, go, go, go, go.
我们要不要再来？
Shall we go again?
所以我们有粒子“C”凯瑟琳
So we have particle "C"-- Catherine--
在粒子“J”詹姆斯的轨道上
in orbit around particle "J"-- James--
激发粒子“E”爱德华
powerize particle "E"-- Edward--
跟着“C”，变成一个新的实体
follows "C", becomes a new entity.
“C”加“E”
"C" plus "E"
这就导致“J”的衰变
which causes "J" to disintegrate.
♪ 如果我能带你上到天堂
♪ If I could take you up in paradise above ♪
♪ 如果你会告诉我我是你唯一的爱
♪ If you would tell me I'm the only one that you love ♪
♪ 生命将会是一个美梦，亲爱的
♪ Life could be a dream, sweetheart. ♪
“爱德华·沃尔特斯，一位本地机修工
"Edward Walters, a local garage mechanic
“以及业余物理学家
"and amateur physicist
“扔下了一颗重磅炸弹在国际物理学研讨会上
"dropped a bombshell on the international physics symposium
“公布一个方程式，使得…
"with the announcement of a formula that makes
苏联夸耀太空成就  未知天才点亮原子热
“用喝而何子火箭…
"interplanetary travel
“…进行星际旅行成为切实可能”
"by nu-cu-lear rocket a real possibility."
核子
Nuclear.
我就说喝而何子，教授
I said nu-cu-lear, professor.
核子
Nuclear.
照片不错
Good picture.
这一定得是…
This has got to be
有史以来有谁为讨好女人而做过最愚蠢的事情
the dumbest thing anybody ever did to impress a dame.
对，特别是你还指望跟她说话
Yeah. Especially one that expects you to talk to her--
她很聪明的
she's smart.
闭嘴，弗兰基
Shut up, Frankie.
艾迪
Eddie
你几乎都没读完高中
you hardly finished high school.
你怎么能指望蒙混过关？
How do you expect to get away with this?
我懂好多科学的事情
I know a lot about science.
打扰了
Excuse me.
艾德·沃尔特斯？
Ed Walters?
你是哪根葱？
Who the hell are you?
比尔·莱利，泰晤士报
Bill Reilly, Times.
是吗？
Yeah?
鲍勃·罗塞蒂
Bob Rosetti.
这地方是我的
I own the place.
哦，嗨，罗塞蒂先生
Oh, hey, Mr. Rosetti.
那么你是否惊讶发现有这么一位…
So were you surprised to find out you had such a
…优秀的员工？
...brilliant employee?
惊讶？你以为我为何雇佣他？他是个天才
Surprised? Why do you think I hired him? He's a genius.
喂，艾德，很多老百姓都想知道…
Hey, Ed, a lot of folks are wondering
像你这样的普通人怎么能有这么先进的想法？
how an ordinary guy like yourself could come up with such advanced ideas.
我想这个我能回答
I think I can answer that.
哈罗，爱德华
Hello, Edward.
恭喜
Congratulations.
谢谢你
Thank you.
你看，事实上我们现在才开始理解…
You see, the fact is that we're only now just beginning to understand
智能的真正本质
the true nature of intelligence.
那么你是？
And you are?
詹姆斯·莫兰德
James Morland.
是…？
With the, uh...?
塞拉斯·潘恩学院
Silas Paine Institute.
实验心理学
Experimental psychology.
我们学到的是，我们称之为天才的那种东西
We're learning that, uh, that thing that we call genius
那是一种可以做出直觉突破的能力
that is the ability to make intuitive breakthroughs
几乎可以在任何地方发展出来
can flower almost anywhere.
难道不是这样的吗，爱德华？
Isn't that so, Edward?
你是专家
You're the expert.
是的，我就是
Yes. Yes, I am.
这就是我来这里的真实原因
That's really why I'm here.
哦，当然除了来拿我的车以外
Oh, apart from to pick up my car, of course,
我相信现在已经修好了吧
which I trust is ready by now.
我们打算研究你
We'd like to study you.
研究我？
Study me?
你的大脑，你的思考过程
Your brain. Your thinking processes.
这是一个绝佳的机会来增进我们对人类知识的理解
It's an extraordinary opportunity to increase our understanding of human knowledge.
你怎么说？
What do you say?
我们能指望你吗？
Can we count on you?
同行对同行
One, uh, colleague to another.
你们很多人可能认得这个测试
Many of you may recognize this test.
这是经典的心理健康和发育考试的变体
It's a variation on the classic P.C.& D. examination.
沃尔特斯先生将有十分钟的时间来完成这个系列
Mr. Walters will have ten minutes to complete the series.
你会在这个盒子里找到第一个问题
You will find the first problem inside this box.
你准备好了吗，艾德？
Are you ready, Ed?
- 其实…  - 开始计时吧，请
- Actually... - Start the clock, please.
是啊，呃…
Yes, uh...
是的，相当…
Yes, quite, uh...
相当让人佩服
Quite impressive.
现在我们进入第二阶段
Uh, now we move on to phase two.
第二阶段？
Phase two?
对，我们，已经测试了实验对象的动作能力
Yes, we've, uh, tested the subject's motor ability.
现在是时候测试他的常识了
Now it's time to test his general knowledge--
这个方面，我必须招认…
something which, I must confess
我一直相当好奇…为此目的
I've been quite curious about--and to that end
我设计了一系列的多项选择题
I have devised a series of multiple choice questions--
一共50道题
50 in all--
有相对论、牛顿物理学、物理化学、当然还有…
on relativity, Newtonian physics, physical chemistry and of course
一些基本的量子力学
some basic quantum mechanics.
实验对象有18分钟的时间来完成这个系列
The subject has 18 minutes in which to complete the series.
呃，请关灯
Uh, lights, please.
你要不要坐下？
Would you like to sit down?
投影机
And, uh, projector.
开始计时
Start the clock.
- 借过  - 借过
- Excuse me. - Excuse me.
借过
Excuse me.
我做完了
I'm done.
就这些？
That it?
在今天的一场集中智商测试中
In an intensive IQ Test today,
年轻的汽车机修工艾德·沃尔特斯得到186分
young auto mechanic Ed Walters
将自己跻身于百分之零点零零零零…
placing him in the top point-zero-zero-zero...
他通过了吗？
Did he pass?
那是我们的艾迪
That's our Eddie!
来啊，提提我们的修理厂
Come on, mention the garage.
来啊，鲍勃&艾尔…
Come on... Bob and Al's...
鲍勃&艾尔
Bob and Al's...
派拉蒙新闻
在白宫，艾森豪威尔总统
At the White House, President Eisenhower
嘲笑了苏联宣称在太空竞赛中跃居领先地位
scoffed at the Soviet claims to have leapt ahead in the race to space.
他摒弃了那条红色流言
He dismissed the red rumors,
说太空第一人将会吃热狗做午餐
saying that the first man in space will have hot dogs for lunch...
而不是甜菜汤
not borscht.
而那个能把我们送上去的人名叫什么？
And the name of the man who could put us there?
艾德·沃尔特斯
Ed Walters.
我以前看错他了
I was wrong about him.
他根本不是一个天才白痴
He's not an idiot savant at all.
他是货真价实的
He's the real thing--
他是白痴中的白痴
he's an idiot idiot.
油污小子是个天才
The boy grease-pit genius.
就像他的导师阿尔伯特·爱因斯坦
And like his mentor, Albert Einstein,
年轻的艾德·沃尔特斯梦想解决宇宙的奥秘
young Ed Walters dreamed of solving the mysteries of the universe.
要是你去掉明星崇拜，你自己就会看得出来
If you'd get the stars out of your eyes you'd see for yourself.
詹姆斯
James!
我们都将乘坐核子火箭引擎去月球度假
Before long, we'll all be going to the Moon for the weekend on nuclear rocket engines
还外带省了我们的燃油费
and save on our fuel bills in the bargain.
你实际读过他那篇惊天动地的论文吗？
Have you actually read this stupendous, earth-shattering paper of his?
没有
No.
你没有吗？
You didn't?
我很惊讶，还以为你会拼死拼活把它拿在手里看呢
I'm surprised. I thought you'd be dying to get your hands on it.
你知道，作为一名数学家同行
You know, as a fellow mathematician.
各地的数学家和物理学家们
Mathematicians and physicists everywhere
正将这一超凡的新理论放在显微镜之下
are putting this startling new theory under the microscope...
是我
It's me.
仔细检查这个简单的汽车机修工的数学光辉
...to examine in detail the mathematical brilliance of this simple garage mechanic
他相信，在自由的土地上…
who believes, in the land of the free
以及勇者的国度里，没有什么不可能的事
and the home of the brave, nothing is impossible.
再按一次喇叭，爱德华
Do the horn again, Edward.
对对 [德语]
Ja, ja.
[ “第13号小夜曲”]
阿尔伯特，我们有自己的敞篷车了
Albert, we have our convertible.
好啊好啊
Good, good.
这就像是出海，还不会打湿
This is like sailing, without the wetness.
这是你的杰作，爱德华
Wonderful thing you have made here, Edward.
你怎么不笑呢？
Why aren't you smiling?
我想我得告诉凯瑟琳实话
I think I've got to tell Catherine the truth.
不不，这太早了
No, no, it's too soon.
她爱错了人，博士
She's falling in love with the wrong guy, doc.
对，但那是爱
Ja, but it's love.
爱德华，那是爱
Edward, it's love.
凯瑟琳？
Catherine?
不，谢谢了
No, thank you.
艾德
Ed.
我正要问你
I was going to ask you
这里你为何要用这个运算符？
why you use that operator there?
我总是问自己同样的问题
I often ask myself the same question.
对
Yeah.
简直是灵光闪现
It's just a stroke of brilliance.
好像，我就差一点可以把它算明白了
Like, I'm just so close to figuring it out.
前方有麻烦
Trouble ahead.
也许，也许不是
Maybe, maybe not.
要是她发现我们理论中的缺陷呢？
What if she finds the flaw in our theory?
放心，我们削弱她的信心就好了
Easy. We just undermine her confidence.
哦，我们不应该那么做
Well, we shouldn't do that.
怎么？
How?
那样我们就会既说不清又反应迟钝
We'll be obscure and obtuse.
也许你把有些事看得理所当然了
Maybe you're taking something for granted.
要是你质疑一切会怎样呢？
What if you question everything?
看看它
Look at it
从一个完全不同的角度
from an entirely different perspective.
质疑一切
Question everything.
阿尔伯特舅舅…
Uncle Albert...
这个可能是对的吗？
could this be right?
怎么啦？
What?
我知道这种表情，我做错什么了？
I know that look. What did I do?
我从没用这种方式检视过它
I never saw it this way.
我不知道我刚才在想什么
I don't know what I was thinking.
失陪
Excuse me.
你对她说什么了？
What did you say to her?
你为什么要让他们把你吓成这样？
Why do you let them scare you off like that?
他们是世界上最厉害的头脑
They are the greatest minds in the world.
又怎样？谁说他们无所不知？
So? Who says they have all the answers?
等等，谁说什么话了？
Wait. Who says what?
谁说你不是世界上最厉害的头脑之一？
Who says you're not one of the greatest minds in the world?
哦，我可不像你
Well, I'm not like you.
你是天生的
You're a natural.
你…你就像是他们中的一员
You're just like one of them.
- 不，我不是  - 是的，你是
- No, I'm not. - Yes, you are.
相信我，我不是
Believe me, I'm not.
哦，对…你更年轻
Oh! Well, okay-- you're younger.
重点在于
The point is,
你不只是什么傻傻的汽车机修工
you're not just some dumb garage mechanic.
你是个天才，而我只是…
You're a genius, and I'm just...
我不知道我是什么
I don't know what I am.
什么？你是什么？
What? What are you?
一个家庭主妇？
A housewife?
几乎是吧
Almost.
我认为你不止如此
I think you're more than that.
[ 模仿白兰度 ]：女士，你唯一害怕的就是你自己
[ imitating Brando]: Lady, the only thing you're afraid of is yourself.
等等，我能不能问你一件事？
Wait. Can I just ask you something?
什么？
What?
是什么，呃…
What, um...
你为什么那么做？
Why do you do that?
什么？
What?
白兰度
Brando.
我只是想逗你笑
I'm just trying to make you smile.
那么…
Well...
谢谢
Thanks.
再见
Bye.
这样最好
It's for the best.
我们稍微挤压一下大脑，给心灵腾出空间
We squeeze the brain a little to make room for the heart.
又或许偶然是大设计的一部分？
Or maybe accidents are part of the grand design?
如果你导致了偶然，那它就不是偶然了
If you cause the accident then it is not an accident.
啊，对对
Ah, ja, ja.
你知道，偶然的问题在于你不能预测其结果
You know, the trouble with accidents is you can't predict the outcome.
啊，所以说也许凯瑟琳会爱上我们中的一个
Ah! So-So maybe Catherine will fall in love with one of us.
你真是个梦想家，李卜克内西
You are such a dreamer, Liebitzrecht.
哦，哦，真抱歉，你在睡觉吗？
Oh! Oh, I'm sorry. Were you sleeping?
哦，凯瑟琳，没有
Oh, Catherine, no.
我只是在休憩
I was just in repose.
你去哪儿啦？
Where were you?
在思考
Thinking.
我在担心你
I was worried about you.
担心我思考？
That I was thinking?
我也是
Me, too.
不，我担心你在生我的气
No, I was worried that you were angry with me
因为这是一件我不能够承担的事情
since it's the one thing I would not be able to bear.
请你原谅一个傻老头
Please forgive a foolish old man.
哦，不不不
Oh, no, no, no.
你并没有…
You weren't being...
哦，也许有一点吧
Well, maybe a little.
是我的缘故
It was me.
他会告诉我该思考什么
He'll tell me what to think.
谁？
Who?
我的笔记本！我以为把它弄丢了呢
My notebook! I thought I lost this.
凯瑟琳，谁？
Catherine, who?
我爸爸…那颗彗星…周五，10点35
My dad... the comet...Friday, 10:35.
亲爱的 [德语]
Liebchen...
我知道我们取笑你的詹姆斯
I know we make fun of your James.
我们叫他“老鼠男”和“啮齿国王”
We call him "the rat man" and "the rodent king."
还有“次等教授”
And "the lesser professor"
- 对  - 还有“粪便心理学家”
- Ja. - and "the excremental psychologist."
对…还有“猴唇爵士”
Ja...and "sir monkey lips."
“黑猩猩皮条客”
"Chimp pimp."
这些都到此为止
This all stops now.
我对你的希望是
What I wish for you:
你走出去，好好生活
You go out and have a good life.
你认真的吗？
You mean that?
我刚跟他说过话
I just spoke with him.
谁？
Who?
跟老鼠…跟詹姆斯
With the rat... with James.
明天我们一起出去，我们来一次远足
Tomorrow, we all go together, and we have an excursion.
哈罗？有人迷失在…
Hello? Someone lost in...
哈罗
Hello.
我们听见叫喊声
We heard screaming.
- 叫喊？  - 对对
- Screaming? - Ja, ja.
我们在找爱因斯坦教授
We are looking for professor Einstein.
他说你们在一起
He said you would be together.
哦，对，但不在这里
Uh, yes, but not here.
我正要跟他去出海
I'm going sailing with him.
哦，出海…当然啦
Oh, sailing... of course!
我们…我们搞错了
We were... we were mistaken.
我们从没出过海
We never go sailing.
真的吗？
Really?
他说鱼不想吃我们刚吃的东西
He says the fish don't want to eat what we have just eaten.
我最好查看一下这个
I'd better check on this.
不不，他没事
No, no! He's fine.
不要碰任何东西
Don't touch anything.
安静
Quiet!
这就是我们在物理学中缺失的：喊叫
This is what we miss in physics: screaming.
如果有人喊叫，一般来说就是我
If anybody screams, it's usually me.
哦，拜托不要，不要碰任何东西
Uh, please, don't, don't touch anything.
你就让那些老鼠四处乱跑，是吗？
You let the rats run around like that, eh?
你很民主
Very democratic of you.
18个月的实验研究付之东流
18 months of experimental research gone!
哦，那些猴子
Oh, the monkeys!
看得出你很忙
It's plain to see you're very busy.
我们另找时间再来
We come back another time.
心理学家啊…好疯狂
Psychologists... So crazy!
走
Go!
哦，我不明白
Well, I don't understand it.
他总是做什么都提早10分钟
He's always ten minutes early for everything.
时间再长我们就要错过风了
Any longer, we lose the wind.
好了，够了，我们出发
Okay, that's it. We're set.
我非常失望
I'm very disappointed.
我原本还期待能更好地了解他呢
I was looking forward to getting to know him better.
好吧，也许下次吧
well, maybe next time.
真漂亮
It's pretty.
- 抱歉  - 没关系，你没事吧？
- Sorry. - It's all right. You okay?
阿尔伯特舅舅…
Uncle Albert...
省省吧
cut it out!
听着，凯瑟琳
Listen, Catherine,
- 有件事我得告诉你  - 不，听着，呃
- there's something I have to tell you. - No, listen, uh...
我知道阿尔伯特舅舅和所有人…
I know that Uncle Albert and everybody
想让我们…你知道的
wants us to... you know.
- 但还有一件事  - 不，你得让我说完
- But there's something else... - No. You have to let me finish.
只不过那个…
It's just that...
就是，两个人之间的爱情…
Well, love between two people, uh...
抱歉
Sorry.
阿尔伯特舅舅
Uncle Albert!
我在操控这条船
I'm steering the boat.
爱情…
Love...
不
No.
有共同目标和兴趣的人…
People who share common goals and interests...
你听说过绿藻色吗？
Did you ever hear of the color algae?
没有
No.
总之，重点在于，艾德，那个…
Anyway, the point is, Ed, that, um...
你不能选择你会爱上谁
you can't choose who you're gonna love.
哦，这我知道
Well, I know that.
你知道吧？它就是自然发生的
You know? It just happens.
而且我认为你是个正派的人
And I think you're a decent person
而且我尊重你…
and I respect you...
我也尊重你
I respect you, too.
谢谢你，而且我知道你对我的感觉
Thank you. And I know how you feel about me.
只不过你不能…
It's just that you can't...
你不能期望一个你刚认识的人…
you can't expect somebody who you've just met--
一个几乎不了解你的人突然就说…
somebody who hardly knows you to suddenly say...
我爱你
I love you.
我明白，那没关系
I understand. That's okay.
不，我爱你
No, I love you.
我的确爱
I do!
我的确爱，我说出来了！
I do! I said it!
你爱我？
You love me?
对！我爱你！
Yes! I love you.
- 阿尔伯特舅舅，拜托你别那样了好吗？  - 你停手好吗？
Uncle Albert, would you please cut that out? - Would you stop?
现在我可以自己来了
I can do it myself now.
哇呼
Wahoo.
你们感觉到了吗？
Did you feel that?
对
Ja!
在某个地方，一个原子与另一个原子发生了碰撞
Somewhere, an atom collided with an atom
这个又与一个原子碰撞，如此持续
that collided with an atom, and so on
一直到碰撞了我们
until it collided with us!
敬原子…
To atoms...
那些性感的小变态
those sexy little kinkies.
就说你认为自己爱上了这个…
Suppose you think you're in love with this...
这个机修工，是吧？
this mechanic, do you?
是的！艾德！
Yes! Ed!
我爱上了他
I'm in love with him!
让我来解释…
Let me explain...
这是…这是…
It's...it's...
这是一种迷恋
it's an infatuation.
这不是爱
It's not love.
他长相讨人喜欢，他很受欢迎…
He's pleasant-looking, he's, he's popular...
阿尔伯特舅舅喜欢他
Uncle Albert likes him,
所以，很自然你感觉到吸引，不过…
so, naturally, you feel attracted, but it...
它不会持久
it won't last.
我们所拥有的就会持久
What we have will last:
共同的目标和兴趣
Common aims and interests...
语言沟通…
verbal communications...
财务安全…
financial security...
智力的兼容
intellectual compatibility.
那爱情呢？
What about love?
听着像是100美元的刹车活儿，弗兰克
Sounds like a hundred-dollar brake job, Frank.
连动杆报废，艾德？
Busted tappets. Ed?
啥？
Huh?
你怎么想的？
What do you think?
她爱我
She loves me.
我以为这就是你的目的啊
I thought that was the idea.
你一直没告诉她，是吧？
You haven't told her, have you?
我一直在尝试
I've been trying.
啊，什么也别告诉他们，我就这么说
Ah, tell 'em nothing, that's what I say.
没那么难
It's not that hard.
你只要给她打电话，然后说
You just call her up and say,
“你好，我是个撒谎的油腻猴子”
"Hello. I'm a lying grease monkey."
别烦我，行不行？
Leave me alone, will you?
会没事的
It's going to be all right.
她爱我
She loves me.
它会不会有效？
Will it work?
你永远不知道
You never know.
我以前见过这个
I've seen this before.
对啊，所有的报纸上都有：
Well, yes, it's been in all the papers:
艾德·沃尔特斯的冷聚变
Ed Walters' cold fusion.
不不，我是说几年前
No, no, I mean years ago...
某个地方
somewhere.
首先我想说，我骗你…
First I want to say, "I lie you...
我…我爱你
"I-I love you.
我是个…是个骗子
I'm a l... a liar."
一直以来有些事情…
There's been some things
我没有完全诚实以对
that I haven't been completely honest about,
而我愿意…
and, um, I would like the...
等一下，凯瑟琳
Just a minute, Catherine.
（地球停转之日）
爱德华·沃尔特斯？
Edward Walters?
是？
Yes?
安静，跟你说话你才说
Quiet. Speak when you're spoken to.
动作自然，回话保持简短
Act natural. Keep the answers short.
爱德华…爱德华，我要你来见见…
Edward... Edward, I want you to meet
合众国的总统
the President of the United States.
艾克？
Ike?!
你是…你是…
You're... you're...
你是那个…
you're the...
你是艾森豪威尔总统
You're President Eisenhower.
哦，至少到下次选举前是
Well, at least until the next election.
呣，这是什么特殊的…时机吗？
Um, some special... occasion?
我正在等一个人…
I'm expecting someone...
一个朋友…
a friend...
凯瑟琳
Catherine.
凯瑟琳·博伊德？
Catherine Boyd?
对
Yes.
阿尔伯特·爱因斯坦的外甥女
Albert Einstein's niece.
我必须告诉她一件事
I have to tell her something.
哦，小伙子，关于这个引擎…
Well, son, about this engine...
呃，我们何时能看到一台可工作的原型机？
Uh, when can we see a working prototype?
一台原型机？
A-A prototype?
俄国人已经宣布他们要在一年内拥有一台可工作的模型
The Russians have announced that they'll have a working model within the year.
总统想要发表一个声明说…
The President would like to make an announcement that...
我们正在新泽西这里制造一台原型机
we are building a prototype here in New Jersey.
我们今晚有个记者招待会
We have a press conference tonight.
七点钟在研讨会上
7:00 at the symposium.
我希望可以告诉他们我们将准备就绪，时间在…
I'd like to be able to tell them we'll have something ready by say, um...
七点吗？
7:00?
到时艾森豪威尔告诉大家好消息
Then Eisenhower tells everyone the good news!
有好消息吗？
There's good news?
关于原型机的
About the prototype!
爱德华知道这事吗？
Does Edward know this?
当然！这实际上是他的主意！
Sure! It was practically his idea!
来吧，我们走
Come on, let's go!
他们在前门等我们
They're waiting for us out front!
哦，我的天
Oh, my god.
打扰了
Excuse me.
凯瑟琳·博伊德？
Catherine Boyd?
我见过你的朋友爱德华
I met your friend Edward.
你一定非常自豪吧
You must be very proud.
我对他有很强烈的感觉
I have very strong feelings about him.
（看彗星）
我们应该离开这个国家
We should leave the country!
不要慌张
Don't panic!
那我们应该什么时候慌张
When should we panic--
当他们因叛国枪毙我们的时候？
when they shoot us for treason?
他们不会因叛国而枪毙你
They don't shoot you for treason.
我认为是电刑
I think it's electrocution.
艾德，那是艾德
Ed. It's Ed!
凯瑟琳在哪里？
Where's Catherine?!
跟艾森豪威尔在一起
With Eisenhower!
退后
Back!
待在后面，先生
Stay back, sir!
凯瑟琳！停下！
Catherine! Stop!
- 那不是，呃…  - 沃尔特斯！
- Isn't that, uh...? - Walters!
艾德
Ed!
凯瑟琳
Catherine!
凯瑟琳，站住！
Catherine! Stop!
恭喜，年轻的女士
Congratulations, young lady.
我跟梅米求婚的时候也是一样的感觉
I felt the same way when I proposed to Mamie.
总统先生，我认为你最好是…
Mr. President, I think you'd better get...
没关系没关系，停车
It's okay. Okay. Stop the car.
那不是艾德·沃尔特斯吗？
Isn't that Ed Walters?
对，是他
Yeah, that's him.
有什么问题吗？
Some kind of problem?
我们为什么停车？
Why'd we stop?
凯瑟琳…
Catherine...
不要跟我说话
Don't talk to me,
你撒谎，你造假，你伪装
you liar, you fake, you phony...
你发现了
You found out.
你怎么会以为我有那么笨？
How could you think I was that stupid?
我没认为你笨，你怎么发现的？
I don't think you're stupid. How'd you find out?
我算出来的，好吗？
I figured it out, okay?
我就是算出来了
I just figured it out.
我把两个两个放在一起
I put two and two together--
- V除以R等于H  - 那个方程式？那太棒了，太好了！
- V over R equals H... - The formula? That's fantastic! That's great!
住手！你这假…
Stop it! You fake...
吻我吧
Just kiss me.
什么？
What?
这就来，艾克！
Be right there, Ike!
不着急
Take your time!
总统以为你在跟我求婚
The president thinks that you are proposing to me,
所以亲吻我吧
so just kiss me.
我们有好多麻烦呢
We're in a lot of trouble here.
我看着是同意了
Looks like a yes to me.
对，是啊
Yes, it does.
你…你这机修工
You... you mechanic.
看？我对于你就是这样，就是个机修工
See? That's all I am to you, just a mechanic,
- 对吧？  - 是的
- right?  - Yeah!
你的名字真的是艾德吗？
Is your name really Ed?
是的，是艾德
Yes, it's Ed.
你真的在一家汽修厂工作？
Do you really work at a garage?
对，就在那家汽修厂你第一次见到我就爱上我
Yes, a garage where you fell in love with me
记得吗？
remember?
那是真的，是事实
That's real. That's true.
好疼
That hurts!
就一会儿，艾克
One second, Ike!
哦，老天在上…
Oh, for God's sake...
你知道吗？
You know what?
什么？
What?
你必须知道
You had to know.
你必须知道你的一个特质
Something in you had to know.
你不蠢
You're not dumb.
不，我蠢！
Yes, I am!
- 不，我蠢  - 不，我认为你以前想随波逐流
- Yes, I am! - No, I think you wanted to go along with it.
事实上，我认为你需要这样
As a matter of fact, I think you needed to.
某种程度上，你应该感谢我
In a way, you should be thanking me.
感谢你？
Thanking you?
老天爷
Geez...
这就来了，艾克
Be right there, Ike!
你咬我
You bit me!
抱歉，艾德
Sorry, Ed.
抱歉咬了你
Sorry about that.
听着，艾德
Listen, Ed.
你说得对
You're right.
我从你身上学到了不少东西，知道吗？
I've learned quite a bit from you, you know?
我有着…
I have a...
我有很厉害的头脑，我应该信任它
I have a great brain and I should trust that.
- 对  - 而且…而且不在于你是做什么的
- Yeah. - And...And it's not about what you do.
而在于你是什么样的人
It's about who you are.
所以，这是我跟你学到的
So, I've learned that from you.
所以要谢谢你
So, thank you.
假货
Fake.
阿尔伯特…怎么啦？
Albert...what's going on?
凯瑟琳刚刚发现
Catherine has just found out
爱德华并不真的是个科学家
that Edward is not really a scientist.
他只不过是一个汽车机修工
He is simply an automobile mechanic.
一个汽车机修工懂个啥玩意儿的冷聚变？
What the hell does an automobile mechanic know about cold fusion?
一点不懂，一切都是个大谎言
Nothing. It's all a big lie.
四月愚人节？
April Fool's?
我们本来没有恶意
We meant no harm.
只是几个老人…
Just foolish old men...
所以关于冷聚变我是对的，是吗？
So I was right about the cold fusion, wasn't I?
凯瑟琳，你有没有意识到
Catherine, do you realize
你已经最终证明了我的方法是不可能的
that you have proven conclusively that my approach is impossible?
结论性的
Conclusively.
这我知道，但你说的是…
I knew that, but you said that...
对，我的意思是
Ja. I meant that
我不能证明或证伪它
I could not prove it or disprove it.
因此，我不能发表它
Therefore, I could not publish it.
我做到了一件你做不到的事情？
I did something that you couldn't do?
对，这是，呃，数学
Ja. It's, uh, mathematics.
我一向在数学上很糟糕
I was always terrible at mathematics.
教授…
Professor...
艾德·沃尔特斯的核燃料理论
Ed Walters' atomic fuel theory.
一篇未发表的，阿尔伯特·爱因斯坦的论文
An unpublished paper of Albert Einstein's
30年前写的
written 30 years ago.
先生们，它们是一样的
Gentlemen, they are identical.
在各方面都是一样的
In every respect, identical.
你是在指控艾德·沃尔特斯剽窃吗？
Are you accusing Ed Walters of plagiarism?
难说
Hardly.
我是在指控艾德·沃尔特斯和爱因斯坦教授
I'm accusing Ed Walters and Professor Einstein
以及他的同仁们，进行…呃…
and his colleagues... of, um...
进行彻头彻尾的欺诈
of outright fraud.
冷聚变不过是个骗局罢了
Cold fusion is nothing more than a hoax.
如果你们愿意耐心等等我们
If you will please bear with us
爱因斯坦教授有一项声明要发布
Professor Einstein has a statement to make.
谢谢你，总统先生
Thank you, Mr. President.
女士们先生们
Ladies and gentlemen,
詹姆斯·莫兰德博士是对的
Dr. James Morland is correct.
冷聚变是一场骗局
Cold fusion is a hoax.
这场骗局如此聪明，如此大胆，如此机密
A hoax so brilliant, so daring, so secret
地球上知道这件事的人不超过5人
not more than five people on the planet Earth know about it.
我们称之为“红甘蓝行动”
We called it "Operation Red Cabbage."
但现在，我们可以透露
But now, we can reveal
通过我的同事博伊德小姐的努力
through the efforts of my colleague, Miss Boyd
还有沃尔特斯先生
and Mr. Walters--
两个最优秀的头脑
two of the finest minds
我很荣幸地获知…
it has ever been my privilege to know--
我们已经证明了…
we have proven...
俄国人声称在冷聚变太空竞赛中取得的跃进
the Russian claim to have leapt ahead in the space race with cold fusion
不过是无稽之谈
is nothing but hot air.
个人而言，我认为…
Personally, I think
任何这一类的竞赛…武器或是太空
any race of this nature--arms or space--
都完全是蠢事
is complete foolishness.
非常感谢
Thank you very much.
一次大师级的行动，各位
A master stroke, gentlemen.
这是一次学院的胜利
A triumph for the institute.
凯瑟琳，亲爱的，你一定要了解
Catherine, darling, you must understand.
我说的话都是出于善意
I said what I said in good faith.
阿尔伯特
Albert
喂，阿尔伯特舅舅，这次不会成功的
Uncle Albert, that's not going to work this time.
不幸，凯瑟琳，这次是真的
Unfortunately, Catherine, this is the real thing.
拜托，我要去医院
Please, I go to the hospital.
慢点
Slowly.
伙计们，拜托，不过是一点心颤
Boys, please, it's just a little flutter.
拜托，出去吧，看看那彗星
Please, go out, see the comet.
去找几个女孩吧
Go get some girls.
我们要不要给你找一个？
Should we get one for you?
好，红头发的
Ja, a redhead.
留下，爱德华
Stay, Edward.
再见，伙计们
Good-bye, boys.
谢谢过来
Thanks for coming.
我很快会见到你们大家
I will see you all shortly.
在上面
Up there.
不用花什么时间就没事啦
It will be okay in no time.
- 我以为你说过时间并不存在  - 我说没时间
- I thought you said that time doesn't exist. - I said no time.
他啥也没说过
He said nothing.
你们看，我总是想象天堂是一个庞大的图书馆
You know, I always imagined heaven to be one enormous library.
只不过你不能把书带走
Only you can't take out the books.
哦，我要拿我裤子里的一件东西
Oh, I need something from my trousers.
哦，我来拿
Oh, I'll get it.
在左手口袋里
It's in the left-hand pocket.
左手
The left hand.
不，另一个左手
No, the other left hand.
要我找什么？
What am I looking for?
对，就是它
Ja, that's it.
你找到了，谢谢你
You found it. Thank you.
把它拿过来，劳驾
Bring it here, please.
对，我的指南针
Ja, my compass.
我的记忆
My memory is...
跟我的父亲…
of my father
在我五岁的时候
when I was five years old.
我想我那时也是生病在床上
I think I was sick in bed then, too.
他给了我这个指南针
He gave me this compass.
当我第一次把它拿在手中时
When I first held it in my hand,
我就惊讶好奇
I was wonder-struck
是什么力量，无形而又不可感觉
by what force, invisible and unfelt
可能在把握这根针
could be holding the needle.
给，爱德华，你拿着它
Here, Edward, you take this
这样你永远不会迷失道路
so that you never lose your way.
你还要保持你的好奇心
And you keep your sense of wonder.
你们俩都有美好的心灵
You both have good hearts.
不要让你们的大脑干扰你们的心
Don't let your brain interfere with your heart.
（普林斯顿医院 主出入口）
我真的很想谈谈，艾德
I'd really love to talk, Ed.
听着，凯瑟琳
Listen, Catherine,
我从未意图把这事弄到这样疯狂
I never meant for this to get as crazy as it did.
要是我在哪些方面伤害了你，我非常抱歉
If I've hurt you in any way I'm very sorry.
有那么一个短暂的瞬间
For one brief moment there
我真实地被一些非常…卓越的人认真对待
I was actually taken seriously by some pretty...extraordinary people.
那是以前我从未经历过的
And that's never happened to me before.
那感觉太好了
It felt great.
我只希望有朝一日…你能…
I just hope at some point that you can...
…真正相信自己有多么的卓越
...truly believe how extraordinary you are.
我会想你的
I'll miss you.
所以你怎么说？
So what are you saying?
要是我们没有干涉，他们最后会在一起吗？
If we hadn't interfered they would have ended up together?
一件事干涉一件事
Everything affects everything.
我相信每件事都会变好的
I believe everything will turn out fine.
为什么？
Why?
因为我宁愿当个傻傻的乐天派
Because I would rather be an optimist and a fool
也不愿当正确的悲观主义者
than a pessimist and right.
嗯，我们都是傻子
We're all fools.
我们本来应该坐电梯的
We should have taken the elevator.
伙子们，拜托
Boys, please.
你们要吵醒护士了
You're going to wake up the nurses.
向上23度
23 degrees up.
不不不，24度
No, no, no. 24 degrees.
是往下22度
It would be 22 degrees down...
拜托，赶紧的
Please, just do it.
为啥？为啥？
Why? Why?
一个将死之人的愿望
A dying man's wish.
要及时
In time.
可是既然时间不存在…
But since time doesn't exist...
你看见什么？
What do you see?
我看见…我看见往天文台的路
I see... I see the road to the observatory.
还有呢，还有呢？
And, and?
还有那是凯瑟琳
And it's Catherine.
还有呢？
And?
她正朝着观星场地去
She is going towards stargazers' field.
等一下
Wait a minute.
那是艾德刚才去的地方
That's where Edward went.
哎哟，哎哟，但凡有个发生偶然的时候
Boy, if ever there was a time for an accident.
有时候，偶然需要一点帮助
Sometimes, accidents need a little help.
上帝不跟宇宙玩骰子
God does not play dice with the universe
可是我会
but I will.
那是一种什么东西？
What kind of a thing is that?
那是什么？
What is that?
这个，是一台发射机
This is a transmitter.
看着
Watch.
奇哉妙也
Wunderbar!
太好了
Great.
把它推下去
Push it down.
- 把它推下去  - 是吗？
- Push it down.  - Yeah?
不要
No!
我要看看…
I'm going to look at...
拜托
Please.
够了！已经够了！
Enough! Enough already!
我还想她完整无缺地回来呢
I want her back in one piece.
现在是怎么回事，阿尔伯特？
What's happening now, Albert?
马达熄火了
The motor has died.
她驶离了公路进入观星区域
She's turning off the road into stargazers' field.
让我看看
Let me see!
就那么发生了，就“嘣”一下
it just happened. Just boom!
嘣
Boom.
你相信偶然吗？
Do you believe in accidents?
不
No.
这样好正确
This is so right.
这就是我想看到的样子
This is the way I wanted to see it.
你听说过七圣池吗？
Have you ever heard of the Seven Sacred Pools?
在夏威夷？
In Hawaii?
你还好吗，阿尔伯特？
Are you all right, Albert?
好，这对我的心脏很有好处
Ja, this is very good for my heart.
哦，我的天
Oh, my god!
看
Look!
嗨，爸爸
Hi, Daddy.
我想念你
I missed you.
这是艾德
This is Ed,
我爱的男人
the man I love.
在这个世界之外
Out of this world.
怎么样啦？
What's happening?
哇呼
Wahoo.